Guide to the Allegheny Conference on Community Development Collection, 1944-1994 AIS.1973.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny Conference on Community Development Collection
1944-1994
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny Conference on Community Development (Pa.)
AIS.1973.04
5.63 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
This collection contains materials published by the Allegheny Conference on Community Development, publications sponsored by or prepared by the conference, and miscellaneous publications regarding Pittsburgh not sponsored by the Conference but related to community development, 1944-1993.
History
The Allegheny Conference on Community Development (ACCD) was organizaed in 1943 as the Citizens' Committee on Post-War Planning. The Committee was established to improve Pittsburgh from a dirty, smoky, easily flooded place where no one would voluntarily live into an improved city that could benefit from the post-war recovery period. This began a very successful plan that has been copied by many other cities.
The Conference has changed its emphasis to meet special needs within the community and has had three distinct periods of history. In 1946, the Conference, along with Mayor David L. Lawrence, began the smoke control program, construction of flood control dams on the Allegheny and Monongahela Rivers, and urban redevelopment programs including construction of limited access highways, public parking authorities, and forty renewal projects in housing, commercial, industrial, and open space developments. In 1955, the Conference created the Regional Industrial Development Corporation (RIDC) to help diversify the region's economy and create new job opportunities.
The second period of the Allegheny Conference began in 1968 and focused on social issues including developing minority businesses and establishing neighborhood and youth programs. During this period, the Conference also created Penn's Southwest Association, which began marketing the nine couty area of Southwestern Pennsylvania. The ACCD also created ACTION-Housing, Inc., which has created housing opportunities for middle and low income families. Conference Programs entered their third period of history in the late 1970s when the Conference turned its attention to community improvement, public education, and housing improvements. In cooperation with Mayor Caliguiri, Pittsburgh began its second renaissance with an acceleration of downtown construction and housing improvements throughout the community.
In the early 1980s the Conference focused on the slumping local economy and developed a series of initiatives designed to spark targeted sectors of the local economy in order to expand sales of products to federal agencies, improve transportation networks, and to promote advanced technology research, development, and manufacturing. More recently the Greater Pittsburgh Office of Promotion, the Health Policy Institute, and the Public Education Fund have all been created by the ACCD.
Scope and Content Notes
The Collection of the Allegheny Conference on Community Development contains four series including materials published by the Conference, publications sponsored by or prepared by the conference, and miscellaneous publications regarding Pittsburgh not sponsored by the Conference but related to community development. These publications were donated to the ASC by the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs, University of Pittsburgh, who obtained these materials while completing the Pittsburgh Renaissance Oral History Project, funded by a grant from the Buhl Foundation, 1971.
Each series is arranged alphabetically by title or author. Folders 15, 17, 56, 71-74, and 78 are oversized and housed seperately from the main collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Gradute School of Public and International Affairs, University of Pittsburgh, December 1972.
Previous Citation
Allegheny Conference on Community Development Collection, 1944-1993, AIS.1973.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Transportation; Community development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Community development -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Environment; Social action; Associations; Allegheny Conference on Community Development (Pa.)
- Publications by the Alleghenty Conference on Community Development, 1944-1959; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains publications by the ACCD and is arranged into three parts - alphabetical by title (if it is a publication of the conference), alphabetical by committee (if a specific committee composed it), and alphabetical by author (if there was a single author).
  - Allegheny Conference Digest, v. 1-2, no.1, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Basic Steel - Production and Consumption in the Pittsburgh Industrial Area, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Brief History of the Penn-Lincoln Highway, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - County Road Transfer Study, 1958, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Direct Air Transportation Services Between the Pittsburgh District and the Southwest, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Four Counties Take Inventory, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Four County Industrial Data: Pittsburgh District, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Four County Industrial Inventory, Bulletin no. 1-4, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Highway and Bridge Projects and McKeesport Grade Crossing, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Highway Study in Allegheny County, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Housing Survey of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County (Part I), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
  - Housing Survey of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County (Part II), 1946 (Box 1a, Folder 13b)
  - Job Training and Placement in the Pittsburgh Industrial Area, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Lower Hill Cultural Center, Redevelopment Area no. 3, 1953; (OVERSIZED) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Major Highway Projects in the County of Allegheny, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh, Challenge and Response..., 1940s; (OVERSIZED) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pittsburgh - Rebuilding, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Products Manufactured in the Pittsburgh Industrial Area as of December 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Progress on Pittsburgh and Allegheny County's Community Development Program, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Recent Trends in the Housing Market of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Recommended Standards for Recreational Facilities, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Review of the 1949 Report Submitted by the Port Authority of Pittsburgh Survey Committee in Regard to a Proposed Rail-River Truck Terminal... (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Report of the Working Committee, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Study of State Highway Program in Allegheny County, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Committee on Employment, Prospective Labor Force, Employment and Unemployment in Allegheny County, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Conference Staff, Report to the Technical Committee on Smoke Abatement, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Conference Staff, Water Supply Survey, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Refuse Disposal Committee Report, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Special Committee on Industrial Sites, Report on Industrial Cities in Allegheny County, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sub-Committee Reviewing the "Econometric Institute Report", Reports, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Water Supply Committee-First Draft of Report, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Water Supply Committee, Reduction of Acid Content of Streams by: Sealing of Mines and Dilution by Flood Control Reservoirs, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Amos, J.E., Towboat Operations in Pittsburgh Engineer District, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Martin, Park H., Report on Educational Television for Pittsburgh, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Nurnberg, Max, Summary and Recomendations of a Housing Program for Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Nurnberg, Max, Review of Pennsylvania Legislation on Urban Redevelopment and Housing, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Thomas, Robert J., An Analysis of Existing Information Used to Determine Labor-Management Relations in Industrial Areas, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Thomas, Robert J., Domestic Requirements for Solid Fuel in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Thomas, Robert J., Factors Influencing Location in the Work Clothing Manufacturing Industry, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Thomas, Robert J., Labor Relations in the Pittsburgh Industrial Area, Part I: Introductory Report, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Thomas, Robert J., Market Survey of Allegheny County for a Coal Burning Smokeless Stove, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Publications Prepared for or Sponsored by the Allegheny Conference on Community Development, 1945-1958; II.
  Series II contains publications prepared for or sponsored by the ACCD. These publications are arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Brahm, Walter T., Allegheny County Library Survey, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Craig, David W., Summary of Conclusions and Recommendations of Report of Building and Zoning Laws in Allegheny County..., 1950 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Davis, Marie A., Libraries in Allegheny County, Today and Tomorrow..., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Duncan, W.E., et al, Report on Overall Solution to the Transportation Problem of Allegheny County, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, Population Trends in Southwestern Pennsylvania, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, Population Trends in Southwestern Pennsylvania, 1910-1944, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Econometric Institute, Inc., New York, The Long Range Outlook for the Pittsburgh Area, a Comprehensive Study of the Magnitude and Control of Economics and Operative Factors Affecting the Area, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Pennsylvania Economy League, A More Effective Industrial Development Program for the Pittsburgh Region, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Pennsylvania Economy League, A Proposed Refuse Disposal System for Allegheny County, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Pennsylvania Economy League, County-wide Refuse Disposal, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association, Parking Study of the Pittsburgh Central Business District, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Miscellaneous Publications Regarding Pittsburgh, Non-Conference, Related to Community Development, 1944-1966; III.
  Series III contains publications regarding Pittsburgh, not published for or by the ACCD, but related to community development in Pittsburgh. These publications are arranged alphabetically by author.
  - ACTION-Housing, Inc., Pittsburgh, The Press Reports ACTION-Housing's Urban Renewal Impact Study, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - ACTION-Housing, Inc., Pittsburgh, Urban Renewal Impact Study, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Commonwealth Real Estate Co., Pittsburgh, Invitation to Gateway Center (OVERSIZED), 1950s (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Community Planning Services Inc., Project 70: A Force for Pennsylvania's Progress in Recreation, Business and Industry, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Craig, David W., Pennsylvania Building and Zoning Laws - An Allegheny County Appraisal, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Demorest, Rose, Pittsburgh, A Bicentennial Tribute, 1758-1958 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Donley, (Charles) and Assoc., Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Port of Pittsburgh Study, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Donley, (Charles) and Assoc., Port of Pittsburgh Survey, Interim Report (First Phase), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, Recreational Facilities: Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, Population Trends in Allegheny County (1840-1943), 1944 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Ford Foundation, The University of Pittsburgh: A Selective Review with Proposals for Future Paths, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, A Survey of the Care of Chronic Disease in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Nurnberg, Max, A Review of 1949 and Prospects for 1950: Progress and Developments in the Field of Housing in Pittsburgh and Allgheny County (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Parsons, Brinckerhoff, Hogan McDonald, Engineers, Report on Six Proposed Parking Facilities for the Public Parking Authority of Pittsburgh, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Highways, Report on the Penn-Lincoln Highway, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Pennsylvania Economy League, The Problem of Records Management in Allegheny County, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Pittsburgh Area Transportation Study, Final Report, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Pittsburgh Press, First 200 Years...From Fort Pitt to Point State Park, 1959; (OVERSIZED) (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Pittsburgh Press, Pittsburgh's Renaissance, 1953; (OVERSIZED) (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Pittsburgh Press, Progress Unlimited (1943-1963), (OVERSIZED) (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association, A Plan for Pittsburgh's Cultural District - Oakland, 1961; (OVERSIZED) (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association, A Report on Recreational Facilities, Borough of West View, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association, North Side Study, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association, Preliminary Report: Part of a Master Plan Report for the Allegheny Regional Planning Commission, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Pittsburgh Sun-Telegraph, This is Pittsburgh-1953, (OVERSIZED) (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Port Authority of Allegheny County, Report on Testing and Evaluation of the Transit Expressway, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Segoe (Ladislas) Assoc., The Oakland Study, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - United Housing Council, Information on the Housing Act of 1950 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures Prepared by Allegheny Conference on Community Development (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, Offprints in Realtion to the Pittsburgh Renaissance (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Charts (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Robert E. Doherty, Statement at the organizational meeting of the Citizens Sponsoring Committee, May 24, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Addendum, 1946-1993; IV.
  Series IV contains added materials. These materials include publications by the ACCD and other publications related to community development in Pittsburgh.
  - Allegheny Conference on Community Development Publications, 1.
    - A Presentation on the Background, Progress, and Action Required on the Civic Program for the Pittsburgh District, undated (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Mass Transit Report no. 1, May 1947 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Closure of Lower Roadway of Water Street Due to High Water, April 1946 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - A Civic Clinic for Better Living, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Allegheny Conference on Community Development Presents...Pittsburgh, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Public Improvements Committee, Subcommittee on Highways, Report on the Matter of Grade Crossing Elimination in the City of McKeesport, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Annual Report, 1968, 1970, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - A Strategy for Growth: An Economic Development Program for the Pittsburgh Region, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Five Year Economic Development Report, 1984-1989, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - The Future of Our Region: New Ways of Working Together-New Alliances for Improving Our Quality of Life, November 23, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - White Paper Committee, Toward a Shared Economic Vision for Pittsburgh and Southwestern Pennsylvania, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Progress and Prospects: A Report on the Agenda of the ACCD, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - A Regional Leadership Alliance for Western Pennsylvania, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - The Future of Our Region, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Annual Dinner Meeting, Remarks by Vincent A. Sarni, November 25, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Robert B. Pease, Executive Director, 1968-1990, History of the Allegheny Conference on Community Development, undated (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Strategy 21: Building World Class Assets, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Miscellaneous Publications Regrading Pittsburgh, 2.
    - Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh, Annual Report, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Penn's Southwest Association, Annual Report, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 100)